And that was Father Stephen Freeman with Glory to God.
Father Stephen is the priest at St. Anne Orthodox Church in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, and hosts
the Glory to God for all things blog site, which can be accessed from his podcast site
at ancientfaithradio.com.
This is a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever.
more listening to ancient faith.
Radio.com
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels.
demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular
materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in
creation, the union of the scene.
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits' podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and I'm A.S. Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
and Majeska Trudy is taking those calls.
tonight and we're going to get to them in the second part of our show. And now a
word from our sponsor. Lord of Spirits has brought to you by our listeners with
help from the Theria School of Filmmaking. Theria School of Filmmaking is the
first Orthodox film school. The primary instructors Jonathan Jackson, a faithful
Orthodox Christian speaker writer and five-time Emmy award winner. To learn more
about Theria please visit TheriaFilm.org that's THERIA Film.
I feel like we should we should clarify something. Okay. Yeah. And that's because people might make an assumption because they already have film school or school of filmmaking. Sorry.
Is through a Christian educational institution. This is not teaching you how to make like pure flicks or like those straight to DVD movies at Walmart. That is true.
But she's teaching you how to make good things.
Eh.
That's like that is indeed the idea if Rob Zombie had gone to the theory of school of filmmaking
That monster's movie would not exist
We can safely say I
Haven't thought about saying that before today, but now I'm gonna say it at least once a week. Okay
So tonight everyone we're gonna be talking about
Spirits this is yet another word that gets used both in Christian context and also in the general culture
that I'll...
almost never gets defined very precisely, certainly not with any reference to how ancient
people would have understood it in their own languages, times and cultures, is a spirit
a ghost, some kind of disembodied pale green being that's basically human but lacking
materiality, is spirit just an impersonal metaphor for observable collective phenomena,
like school spirit.
For Father Steven, is this all just some tired Scooby Doo plot that would have come?
off if it weren't for those meddling kids. What do you think?
I'm going to decline to comment on that last one because I feel that like mermaids and hobbits,
Scooby Doo is now a culture war minefield. So I'm just going to steer clear of it.
That's true. Right. I mean, other than, you know, we could all agree, scrappy doo,
not a good addition to the show.
Yeah, what was that all about?
I think is safe. That was the the shark jumping moment for Scooby-Doo. Yeah. Yeah. So I'm trying to play it safe now.
I'm going to get myself into trouble at some point in the show, but here at the beginning,
right, let's let's let's play it safe. So, so we're do we begin?
Right. Well, so we're going to start by talking about the words that get translated as
spirit, right? Because our purpose here is to explain what a spirit is. Okay. And so we're
going to start with the words and we're going to see what clues that gives us and proceed from there
as things get more and more complicated. Okay. But one that we talked about way back in the long ago
time in the before time when the
were still around was the way the word Elohim in Hebrew is used in the Old Testament.
Yeah, that's a word some people get excited about. Yeah. So the
that word is translated in different ways. The normal probably, well not probably. The most
common way it gets translated even though it's a plural is as God with a
capital G.
Yeah, right. Because you know, obviously the Old Testament talks about the God of Israel a lot. And so
if that's the way it's most commonly transmitted because that's
whom it is most commonly referring to or to whom it is most commonly referring.
Yes, the one to end a sentence with a preposition.
You can.
I won't turn you in this time.
It deference to you, sir.
I will not do that.
Not one of those rules that I that I like to stand on.
So it's something up with
which I will not put. Yeah, exactly. So, and in that case, as we've mentioned before,
the reason for it being a plural, you will hear this plural of majesty thing, which technically
speaking doesn't exist in Hebrew, and you'll have some pedant point that out to you. But there is
something in Hebrew that we've talked about on the show before called a superlative plural or an
intensive plural.
where something is made plural, the place where I remember we talked about this other than the word Elohim was
Mahaymot or Behemoth
Beast of beasts right which yeah technically
Is a plural a feminine plural so yeah, we're technically could be translated cows
But is used with masculine pronouns.
referred to behemoth as a he and is used to refer to one being and so we understand that to be,
as you said, the beast of beasts or the mountains of mountains, the greatest one, the big one,
the super beast, right? Apparently since it's October, it's Rob Zombie night, I don't know.
But there are places in the Old Testament on anybody's reading, right?
where it is just
being used as the plural for God. So it's used to mean gods, right? It's referring to
gods of the nations, the gods of some particular nation, the household gods of an idolater,
right? There are places, but it's the same word. There are also places where that term is used to
to refer to angels, both fallen and unfallen.
I just refer to as gods.
a lot of these are hidden in English translations
because people get squeamish about them.
Because, and we won't go back all through this again,
as we talked about, the category of monotheism is a late one,
but then once it came around,
you know, we can't say gods for refer to angels
because that makes it sound like we're polytheists.
So, we translate it, they'll change it in English translation
to angels or spirits or something else.
And
And finally, as we've talked about before, there are a few places where Elohim is used
to refer to the spirits of deceased humans.
Yeah, like when the Witch of Endor calls up the Prophet Samuel on the day.
Or the, and we talked about this.
So this is super controversial, so we're not going through it all again, but they're back
in the catalog, the Lord of Suridh's back catalog.
We start
about the ritual for a slave sort of becoming a permanent member of a household in which
they're brought before essentially the ancestors of the clan. And so anybody who hasn't listed
that episode, if you're freaking out, just go listen to the back catalog. You'll find there's
transcripts to you can search them. So what that means is that essentially if you
loop all these together as we've said, the word Elohim is just used to refer to what we might call spiritual beings.
Right. Yeah. Right. And you know, that because we're going through the different words that are used, we need to go through this one, it doesn't give us a lot of help in terms of what a spirit is.
Because all we've basically said is that this word is used to mean spirit.
it. Yeah here's an example.
of thankful. Right. So now we'll move on to the words that are specifically translated as
Spirit. Yeah. Right. So we've got Hebrew, we've got Greek, we've got Latin, these are kind
of the main ones. And we'll talk about English. Yes. Yes. In a special segment. Yes. But
So the Hebrew word that's generally translated as spirit is Rua.
And those of you who may go to Antiochian churches may immediately recognize the Arabic
cognate for spirit.
That word literally means wind.
And so you get some interesting translations sometimes in places where it occurs, right?
So when they're able to...
to train like when it's talking about the spirit of God, right?
Okay.
Or the Holy Spirit.
Or it's very clearly talking about a spirit.
They'll translate it to spirit.
But other places where on an immediate surface read, right?
Spirit doesn't seem to necessarily make a immediate sense.
They'll try and do something with wind.
And one of the most infamous examples of this.
is in Genesis 3 verse 8. Yeah, this is so weird. Which is, which is where Christ comes
walking in the garden to find Adam and Eve, or a man and woman. Is there no at that time?
And it says literally in the Hebrew, it says that that he comes walking in the spirit of
the day. Yeah. So the word there is raw, right?
So he comes to the spirit of the day.
Now, when you look at different English translations,
you will not only find various different translations,
but you will find exactly opposite translations.
Yeah, like some of them, it says in the cool of the day,
and others it literally, it says in the heat of the day.
Yeah.
Or in the breezy part of the day.
Yeah, that's a win.
was blowing. Yeah, like what is I mean that's so bizarre. I've always heard I mean I think the one
that I've heard the most as I was growing up was in the cool of the day and maybe that's what's
I have to go look at the KJ. That's probably King James, because that's what I that's what I grew up
hearing is is that particular. Yeah, yeah, and I think part of what was
as motoring that was both a thought that it referred to the time of the day.
I think that they're trying to pay to picture like oh there's a cool breeze blowing in the afternoon
and so God goes for a walk like we all do you know. It's his common. Yeah so in the past
um we have recommended for people who don't want massive amounts of student debt
like I have to learn ancient languages, but who...
want to do series Bible study to get the any T Bible with the full notes because they
have of course extensive notes on these kinds of things.
And so the note on this verse is kind of interesting because they sort of go all over the place
in the possible ways you could do something with it.
I'm gonna read this everybody.
but don't get lost. Okay, we'll revisit the important parts. Yes. So this is what the
net Bible says about this particular word. The expression is traditionally rendered
cool of the day because the Hebrew word, Roach, can mean, went. You, Kassuto, so this is obviously
one of the scholars, concludes after lengthy discussion at the expression refers to the afternoon
when it became hot and the sun was beginning to decline.
J.J. Niehaus offers a different interpretation of the phrase relating Yom, usually understood
as Day, to an Akkadian cognate Umu, which means Storm, and translate the phrase in the
wind of the storm.
If Niehaus is correct, then God is not pictured as taking an afternoon stroll through the
orchard, but as coming in a powerful wind storm to confront the man and woman with their
rebellion.
In this case, the phrase,
you were.
the sound of the Lord, may refer to God's thunderous roar, which typically accompanies his
appearance in the storm to do battle or render judgment. I had never heard of that last bit before
ever. Only faithfully do I have a heat of the day in the back of my head somewhere.
Yeah. So, and you can sense the influence of the Yahweh as storm god's stuff in there too.
the sound right away. Yeah. Yeah. That him appearing in a storm to do battle or red or judgment
is typically accompanied by a thunderous roar. Give me an example. Anyway. Yeah.
But yes. But so there is something that as usually happens, even with people who are way off
But who are serious scholars?
There is something there that he is
keyed in on, not entirely for the right reason. I don't think. But there's something
there he is. He has keyed in on. And that is a somewhat different understanding of what
the day means. Right. Because it isn't, there is the definite article there in Hebrew.
And when you see references in the Old Testament, for example, to...
the day, right?
Not like one day, like we get in Genesis 1,
like 8 a, but V day,
they're almost always referring to the day of Yahweh,
the day of the Lord.
Yeah, the time where he's going to bring justice.
Right, when he's going to visit, right?
Yeah, like we...
And so yeah,
and so I would submit that you can translate it as he comes
walking in.
the spirit of the day. So, Nehous has indirectly, right, and colored by sort of his other
presuppositions. He has at least pulled out this idea that there is what's going on here
in that phrase is that there's this judgment motif, right? That justice is now going to
be rendered, right? Things are going to be set right. Things are going to be corrected
that have, that have gone wrong.
right. But it is also true, even though here I'm saying you can understand it in
spirit, there are also places where it just clearly means wind. Yeah, sure.
Right. That's clearly just what they're saying. Sometimes the wind is just a wind.
Right. But so in in Hebrew and really indicating behind it and in all these
can't all these cognate languages. There is this
connection, always between the idea of a wind and the idea of a spirit.
Right?
Okay.
Coming out of these Semitic languages.
So then, when we move to Greek, and you get to the word Pnevma, we can use modern Greek
pronunciation for the sake of our Greek listeners and them not keel hauling me.
the Erasmian Kill Hall tonight on a very special Lord of Spirits. So I would be hoisted on my own
p'tard. Nice. Nice. So I caught that reference. The word penefima means breath, wind, or blow.
Yeah, yeah, so almost the same semantic space, semantic range.
range, but not quite, but still pretty much the same breath wind. But here's part of why
that's important, because when the time came to translate the word Rua into Greek, in
places where it clearly is referring to a spirit, in the sense that we use the word spirit,
Bye.
chose the Greek word that means breath, wind, blow. Right? So what that tells us is sometimes
a word has an original meaning and then starts to get used by analogy for something else
and ends up losing its original meaning. Yeah. Right? Like there's the meaning of the word
Drifts in migrates, right? So the
fact that that translation choice was made means that as we're getting into the third century BC
that that idea of wind and breath was still being connected to the idea of spirit.
And just shifted into being a word that means spirit and lost those other meanings.
Yeah.
And that of course also once we get into Greek raises the question of the relation.
between Pneumma and Sikhi, Soul or Soul, right?
That we translate as Soul.
And this is the clearest place to see this probably
as once again in Genesis, but in Genesis 2.
And this is also pretty well applied
to the relationship between the Hebrew Rua and Nefesh,
which is the word that gets translated Soul from Hebrew.
And that's where when God creates Adam, he breathes into Adam's
gospel. And once he has breathed into him, he becomes a living soul.
Yeah, right.
And so when we make a distinction between soul and spirit,
We're making essentially a distinction between
spirit as the animating force in a being and the soul as the life itself. So between animating force and life itself.
Right. So that's a distinction you can make. Right. At least in speech.
Right. Aristotle has that category. Distinctions possible only in speech. Right.
Something's that you can't divide in reality, but you can divide in how you talk about them. Yeah, it's a
conceptual distinction that one can make. Right. Right. So like talking about, you know,
a ray of light, it's brilliance. Right? And you can pull these apart, right? But you can't
actually, they're not different things. Right? Yeah. And so this is why the fact that this is a
possible distinction between animating force and the life itself is why...
You find in different church fathers, different ways of talking about whether a human person is
body, soul, spirit, body, soul, body, spirit, right? These different ways of
of divvying things up. Because some fathers will, for some particular reason, want to make this
distinction like between spirit and soul, between a person.
life and the animating force within them. Right. And so they're making some kind of argument.
Right. They're not writing sort of this objective treatise of no. There are these three things. And if
you say there are not these three things, or label them differently, you are wrong. Yeah, it's not an
anatomy of the invisible element of the human. Yeah. Right. It's they're making some
point down the road and for the purposes of making that point, they make this distinction.
Or because they're making a different point, they don't need to make that distinction.
That distinction isn't relevant to what they're talking about.
And so they don't make it.
Right.
Like if I were just to say human beings have both a material and an immaterial aspect, then
I might just say, we consist of body and soul.
Right.
Yeah.
If someone came again being pedantic
It's like, oh, are you denying that man has a spirit then?
Right.
They would clearly not understand right what you were saying.
Yeah.
So this is not a contradiction.
And a good example in modern internet discussion
for this kind of distinction making
is the perennial question of is blank a sandwich?
Yes, our hot dogs a sandwich.
hamburgers of sandwich is a burrito of sandwich because I've participated in many of these and I have
won every argument. But there's a whole, you know, we call a chicken sandwich a sandwich, but a
hamburger that has the exact same ingredients other than beef versus chicken, we would say that's
a hamburger and not a sandwich. In consistent. Anyway, it's true. So...
But, right, there's not, to be on just sophistry,
that I would use to win those arguments.
There is not an actual right or wrong.
Yeah.
There is no metaphysics or ontology
under which something absolutely is a sandwich
or absolutely is not a sandwich.
I mean, I prefer the argument from authority
where you actually has to have a seal of approval
from the Earl of Sandwich himself.
You're an originalist.
Yeah, when it comes.
just sandwiches. So any ingredient which he did not encounter should not be on a sandwich
by that. That's correct. So, but that's why we're using that as an example. Right. So,
no one who makes the distinction between soul and spirit thinks they're separate,
quote unquote things. They're like objects. Right. These are distinctions made.
in speech for a particular purpose, right? In the same way that we categorize different
foods in different ways for particular reasons, right? Of use and convenience and that kind
of thing, right? So that's Greek. There's a lot of consistency there. And then there's
even more consistency when you get to Latin and you get to the word spiritus, which is
where we get the English word spirit.
Obviously. Yeah. And I mean, we should say that the Greek word,
Pneumat, we have it in English with words like pneumatic and pneumonia,
which all have to do. Neuvratic and Pneumonia. Oh, excuse me.
Excuse me. I had to go to hospital for Pneumonia. Yeah.
No, no Greeks would complain if you pronounced it that way. I guarantee it.
Um, but, uh, um, so...
So, spiritus also means breath or wind or blow.
Right, right.
Pretty much exactly parallel to the Greek.
Now, one small difference is that Latin generally,
this isn't 100% true, but the Latin language, right?
Essentially treat spiritus and anima as synonyms,
on him of being the word for soul.
Yeah.
Now, despite that, because of what we just said, right, about soul and spirit, there are authors who will use them not as synonyms and use them in some technical way, right?
Blood and authors.
Yeah, to distinguish things, right?
But linguistically, right?
In Hebrew and Greek, we're talking about different words that have different cognitive domains
with spiritual synonyms in the language we're not.
Right because of course things are translated into Latin and
You have for example Latin theologians who are influenced by earlier traditions
Right, they will sometimes make more technical distinctions
Between those words. Yeah, and I mean and we do have English words that come from the Latin that mean
Exactly the same kind of concept, right? So like rest, inspiration and my favorite conspiracy, which means breathing together
Literally, but no one uses it that way strangely enough. I don't know why.
Come, let us breathe together and we will overthrow a government.
Oh, we're out of watch list now.
I didn't see which government could be student government.
I actually was impeached as class president and one.
Are you serious?
I'm dead serious.
I wrote out the impeachment, though.
That's glorious. You're a
Where you? Well, no, well, it's a long story. We won't go into it here, but let it did happen.
Student government can be a messy thing.
There's a bunch of people now doing deep Google searches to see if they can discover your high school yearbook.
I don't think it's online.
They would discover many interesting things.
Like there was the first day of all the clubs was picture day.
So I went to every single club on picture day. So it looks like I was in every
club in the school, even though I never went to another meeting.
So I was I was for five minutes in Latin club. There was no Latin club,
except for the day for picture day. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Hey, we have something in
common.
Also, buying your book evidence. Yeah. That's right. Spiritus. Yeah, back to Latin.
Well, no, now we need to move on from Latin to a special segment.
Yes, that's right.
It's time everybody.
Yes, it's been a long time since we've had etymology corner.
And we're going to be talking about English, the English word, ghost, ghost.
It's a great word in English.
And we tend to use it these days to refer to something we're going to talk about later.
But traditionally ghost,
Re-
first two spirits, right? Just it's the general word for spirit. It actually has a kind of a different
origin from these other words we've been talking about from Hebrew, Greek, and Latin, where the
idea of wind and breathing and spirit are all kind of connected together. In English it does not have
that same origin. Father Stephen asked me, is ghost related to gust? And I am sorry to say they're not
They are not cognates.
They do sound a little similar, similar as true, but this is what we call a false friend.
False friend. It'll betray you in the end, everybody.
Unlike Burton Guster, who was a true friend who had never betray.
Yeah.
So, ghost in English, we've also, you know, we've got, for instance, the German word,
geist, which is essentially the same. Ghost in English comes ultimately from A.
a proto-West Germanic word, Geist, G-A-I-S-T, Geist, which comes from a proto-Germanic Geist
Taz, which ultimately comes from a proto-Indo-European route that I'm not going to try to pronounce.
But that proto-Indo-Protor.
The photo-protor.
You're Sanskrit, man.
I know, I know.
It's like Geist, Geist, Geist, Geist, Geist, Geist, I don't know.
Yeah.
I'm not, I'm, yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah.
That one actually ultimately comes from a word that refers to anger or agitation, which
kind of makes you wonder like, well, how did we get from that to the sense of spirit?
And it's the overlapping concept is fear or terror.
Right?
So the idea that when you encounter a spirit, this is what you feel.
And so that's how we get the modern English word ghost.
Interestingly, you know, we mentioned gust, right?
actually it comes from up a root that refers to pouring. So gust and gush.
for instance, are cognate with each other and have this idea of a pouring out. So,
Gust is a sudden pouring out of wind. But yeah, alas, they are not connected together.
But yeah, Ghost does have a cognate in Sanskrit that refers to anger or hatred,
and one in even in Persian that refers to something that's ugly, hateful or disgusting.
So, but generally in Germanic languages, it's all spirit, it just means spirits. But there is
not this sense of breath or wind in the
versions. If fun though, especially if you read stuff that's early modern English and in middle
English, you'll see the word ghostly and used exactly to mean the way we would use the word spiritual.
So a very ghostly person does not mean someone that haunts your house and you know,
a Casper, the friendly ghost kind of thing, but rather a ghostly person is a very spiritual person
and you could even refer to having your ghostly father.
So, I'm just going to suggest to everybody listening home right now,
that next time you contact your father-confresser,
that you refer to him as your ghostly father and just sort of see what happens.
I'm just throwing that out there, for everybody.
I'm ghostly but not religious.
There you go, exactly so, right?
That's a very ghostly thing for you to say.
Like?
Yeah, I just feel so ghostly today.
Yeah, it's too bad. This usage has just gone away.
But that's why of course you see Holy Ghost.
in early English Bibles, because ghost in that period did not mean something spooky or
whatever, it just was the word for spirits.
Later on, it kind of gets separated out from the same concept of spirit to refer to a particular
kind of spirit, which we'll talk about, that concept.
But yeah, so there you go.
That's English ghost.
Father and
So you've got, you know, theme music for both before and after.
I'm glad you had that ready.
Oh yeah, oh yeah.
I was briefly nervous that you wouldn't have it ready.
Not even so much because it would have let down the listeners, but I think you would have
let yourself down.
I, oh, you better believe it.
Absolutely.
If you hadn't had it.
So there you go.
So you've got Hebrew, Greek, Latin, and...
English for this word for spirit.
Right.
And we haven't gotten a ton of help with our main question yet.
No, because, well, basically what we've gotten is that it has something to do with wind maybe.
Right.
Well, we've never really been known to rush on this show.
We're taking our time.
I'm just summarizing where we're at.
Here's where we're at.
Not a lot.
So yeah, we're not focused on
productivity here. So now we can turn to something that maybe we'll give us some more help.
Right, we looked at the words. So let's look at some examples. Right, so we look at some examples
of spirits. For example, in the scriptures. Maybe we can look at them and kind of see what they
have in common. All right, and that might help us define spirit as a category, right, or something.
spoilers it won't help us much, but we're going to go through this anyway. So one example would be
human spirits. And those aren't entirely disembodied. So we hear about a person, like a living person
spirit, right? Like Adam, right? Right. But then there are also the spirits of people that.
continue to exist if exist is the right word, right?
Continue to be to do things after the physical death, right?
Yeah. I mean, and the human question.
And you know, we sing like, for instance, when we're doing a
tricilion memorial, we we we sing with the spirits of the righteous
made perfect. Right. We're talking about departed humans.
Right. And then in that case, it's a spirit to the righteous made
perfect those are good ones. Yes alright.
There's also bad ones.
It's true.
So you've got the Refine ending with Og, who was the last of them, right?
And who we also know from a really creepy, ugrinic tablet where they were offering animal sacrifices
to the Refine so that they would let the newly dead king pass into the underworld.
Yes.
appeasement. Isaiah mentions the refereeing rising up to
meet the devil as he was thrown down into the underworld. Don't try and figure out the
timing on that because just like you've said, what time zone is heaven in? What time zone
is Hades in? Right. And so, and of course, it's always a good time to once again mention
that quote from St. John Chrysostom where he talks about
how people become demons, right?
Which is there was at that time a belief
that if someone died of violent death
or died in some horrible way,
their spirit would come back and mean malicious, right?
And that's of course what a demon is, right?
It's a from a Christian's perspective,
the word day mode just kind of means spirit and Greek,
but from our perspective,
as Christians and from the Jewish perspective,
those are malicious spirits. So that belief from St. John
Chrysostom's time is kind of still around today if you ever have watched a horror movie,
right? You have people who die some kind of violent death and come back in haunt places, right?
And do malicious things. But St. John Chrysostom says that's not how they become a demon.
someone becomes a demon by living a life like the demons by being...
coming like the demons in their life through their sin and wickedness and giving themselves over to the passions.
Yeah, live like a demon now and you will be a demon after you die.
That's what Saint John Chrysostom literally says.
Literally.
Not figuratively.
So there's one example of spirits.
Right.
Then there are of course, as we mentioned, there are angelic or demonic spirits that
were never humans, right? And we know, according to the scriptures, that these are spirits,
regardless of their rank, regardless of fallen or unfallen. These are our spirits that were created by
God.
by Yahweh the God of Israel.
Yeah, they're not
eternal, they're not
uncreated, they are created.
Even though they're
sometimes called Elohim, sometimes called
gods in the Old Testament
and other related literature,
they are not gods the way
he is God, capital G, right?
He is other because they're created by him.
Now, of course, this is in
the biblical correction
broader.
pagan world where they agreed, right, they did not think that the spirits they worship were eternal.
They not only believed that they came into existence at some point, right. We mentioned in
the Thunder Gods episode that there are several places that were identified as pilgrimage sites,
sites where Zeus was born, for example. So they believed they came into being at some point and
they could die, they could be destroyed, they could be defeated.
Right?
Yeah.
going forward. And often as we've talked about not only where they said to sort of reproduce
with each other, but there was the succession myth and sometimes like in Hesseyid multiple
layers of succession where it was acknowledged within the stories that previously some other
God had been the one that was worshipped as the Most High God, but now this other God came
and overthrew him and now he is and now his son came.
and over through him. And so even in, right, the disagreement between, for example, the
Old Testament texts and pagan polyphism from the surrounding nations is not that they
said their gods were eternal or even that their most high god was eternal. And Israel
said no it's Yahweh it's that both have
had this layer of spiritual or divine beings that came into existence. And then in Israel,
there is this other beyond being, right? There is a Yahweh who created them all.
And we should emphasize too that just because the pagan stories say things, for instance,
about them reproducing with each other. That's not what's...
actually happening. That's just simply the story within those pagan religions.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Because they don't have reproductive faculties.
Right. Everyone understood that. And those are late stories. Yeah. Right. Because as we've
talked about before, in reality, there would be one or two gods of a given place.
right but then as larger social units come together they
integrate their beliefs in those gods. And how do you do that? Right? Is it just a bunch of
competing individual gods? Well, no, you could struck this family tree. Right? You can
move them together. Yeah. Right. So even those parts of the story are sort of late to the
late to the party in that way. Right. But yeah. But yeah. So this idea of contingent gods,
That's right, it's that the...
the nations around Israel did not have this idea of anything beyond that layer of these sort of
contingent gods. Yeah. Yeah. All their gods were by their own definition kind of lesser.
Right. Yeah. Right. So even like the word, the word, Daemon in Greek, which was generally applied
to you know spirits of you know this or that lake.
this or that forest, right? Sort of lower degree spirits was sometimes applied to Zeus.
Yeah. So there was less hierarchy there, right? Then there was no kind of ontological hierarchy,
no hierarchy of being there. It was just a question of sphere of authority or what have you.
and that could change.
So then the other
example, the big example of course from scripture of a spirit is the Holy Spirit. And it's it's worth
because this doesn't get talked about as much by anybody, including me right. The section on
Christ, it religion, the Apostle says a lot longer than the section on the Holy Spirit you've probably
notice. Um, get noticed that because frankly there's there's less about the holly's.
spirit in pre-Christian material.
Yeah.
Just not as mentioned in the Old Testament.
Appears, but it was not the subject of a lot of discussion.
Yeah.
Right.
And there's various ways to approach why that is.
Because of the view I have vis-a-vis ancient Israel
and second-temple
Judaism's
Understanding of there being multiple hypostasis of Yahweh the god of Israel
I think it's mainly because the idea of
Yahweh and the spirit of Yahweh being a
Hypostasis of Yahweh like just made sense to them so there was less cause for discussion
Yeah, right like contained within the name the spirit of God was sort of the relationship they needed to understand whereas
whereas the
two powers in heaven literature,
trying to understand the relationship
between father and son, right?
That was more complicated, more murky,
until the incarnation, right?
And so there was much more cause to debate
and discuss and speculate, right?
In second-time Jewish circles.
But because it's sort of less to talk about,
it's worth making a few clear points here
about who the whole...
Holy Spirit is in Scripture, and as that's been sort of defined in theological terms by
the Church.
Yeah, I mean in the fourth century, you get a decent amount of theological reflection
and definition on the Holy Spirit.
Like St. Basil, of course, he's got a whole text on this, right, called on the Holy Spirit.
St. Gregory the Theologian.
he talks about this as well.
it's confirmed in the second ecumenical counsel that the Holy Spirit is divine.
So yeah. Yeah, yeah. And so St. Basil's ultimately going to say that the Holy Spirit is the image
of the Father in a similar but not identical way to the way that the Son is, right? Yeah.
And that's the difference between the sun being generated, the sun being begotten.
right and the Holy Spirit proceeding and as the fathers all say if you ask me
exactly what that means
who knows right yeah I think one of them says if you try to figure out the
difference between the two then you'll go insane yeah remember who that is but
yeah right right yeah yeah so don't try those at home kids yeah to put that the
terms that we were just using and that we use now fairly commonly.
on the show, right? The Holy Spirit is a hypostasis of Yahweh, the God of Israel.
And he is seen in the Old Testament as the presence of God, the theophonic glory cloud,
in the tabernacle and the temple, as the pillar of fire, and the pillar of cloud that leads Israel
as the tongues of flame at Pentecost and descending.
And the manner of his descent was like the descent of a dove at Christ's baptism.
I say that specifically because Holy Spirit did not turn into a bird.
Yes.
It's okay, iconographically, yes, to depict this in this way, but that's only in that icon, by the way.
Yeah.
Don't go around painting birds.
That's not the Holy Spirit.
Right.
But
So that is the, those are the places where we see him, right?
And particularly in terms of the presence, capital P of God, and the tabernacle in the temple,
is clearly a place where you see hypostasis, a localization.
This is God himself.
Yeah, right.
Right.
But this is not the person that Moses spoke to face to face.
Thank you.
And this is not the person who Moses was told he could not see and live.
Right?
This is a third person.
This is where we're going to do the honorable mention about early Japanese Bibles.
You can go for it.
So yes, disclaimer, I do not speak or read Japanese.
But apparently in
early Japanese Bibles. Holy Spirit was translated with the phrase that in Japanese would mean divine
wind, which now right in Japanese readers or speakers, let us know if this is true or not,
it would mean that it's kamikaze, right? Doesn't that mean divine wind?
So I'm sure we're going to get some umakshelies on the email over this. Yes,
Send him actualy's, send corrections, send hate mail accusing him of racism to father Andrew Damon.
There we go. Thank you very much.
You should be.
You know, yeah.
Um,
so then, uh, the father, the son, and the kamikaze.
Yeah. I just doesn't work for me. I can't do that. Yeah. No. Yeah.
So then our question again, what is a spirit?
Right?
Uh, has that helped us?
Well, it was kind of a necessary step, I think, but.
I mean what?
What does a human spirit, the Holy Spirit, and from what we've just said and say a demon
having common?
Yeah.
They're all spirits, right?
But that doesn't really help us define what that we're right, right?
So let's try.
So what is a spirit?
We're still not getting very close.
So let's try what a spirit isn't.
Yes, the F.
apophatic approach. We are Orthodox. We're required to see some apophatic things, but you
can't really say things through apophatic. Can you? Just throw it.
Well, we're going to we're going to we're going to myth bust. So okay, common notions of what
what a spirit is, right? So, um, probably if you ask somebody today, right? So our little
thumbnail for the episode. I found a photo of...
what's that's what's called spirit photography that was very popular in the late 19th and early 20th
century. But today if you ask somebody to picture a spirit they probably picture something sort of
like a force ghost. Yes, right. So Star Wars fans, you may recall in, now let's see did they show
up an episode four, which was just called Star Wars when it first came? No, but in episode five.
Yeah.
Yeah. You get believed in Obi-Wan show up and talk to you.
Oh, yeah. Obi-Wan appears to Luke on Hoth to tell him to go find Yoda.
And then you get in episode six, of course, you get a couple of different force ghost
appearances. So you get Obi-Wan as a force ghost appears to Luke on Dagobah right after Yoda dies.
and then at the very end of the film, you get...
it, you know, Obi-Wan and David Prous.
And canonical.
That's correct.
It's so up on the forest moon of Endor.
And then of course, you know, later, forest ghosts and stuff.
But, but yes, that's right.
So basically you're getting people that are kind of glowy and people shaped.
And they have the same for sale human shape,
like an outline of what
looked like when they were alive, right? It's a deceased person. Right. It's not a deceased person.
If it's an angel, it's an outline of a person with wings. Yeah. Michael Lender perhaps.
Roma Downey, I don't know. Yeah. Christopher Wacken. Or Patrick's Wazey. Yeah,
Till the sun.
So.
But.
Right. It's sort of this hazy outline. Right. Right. Right. And you see this all the time.
See this in the Dr. Strange movie, right? Like Spirit Leads the Body and it's just sort of the vaguely translucent outline of the person.
It's an astral projection, including their clothes.
Right. That's kind of interesting. Whatever the word.
I couldn't have the time. I'm really happy though that it includes the quality.
Well, yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Although I do have to think Beetlejuice was not wearing that outfit when he died.
But anyway.
So, a fair pound. All of those are wrong. Sorry. So, zero spirits, right, are really portrayed
that way in ancient literature or in Scripture.
Well, I mean, where do you get this concept of ectoplasm then? Like what is...
Well, we'll get there in a second.
Okay, I'm just I do have to say
The closest thing you get to that, right, might be in the Greek conception of Hades,
like in Homer's Odyssey, right, when the shades show up.
Yes, shades.
But what that literally is is that's the opposite of a glory outline.
That's the person's shadow.
Yeah.
Right.
That's kind of the closest you would get to something like that, right?
Wow, I'm having all kinds of Peter Pan
issue suddenly. Okay, okay, I'm just going to work on this while you see your next paragraph.
Okay, yeah, that's your own. Yeah. So, but the question moves to, right, if a spirit is something
that can sometimes be seen, right? It's, um, and it's normally invisible, but if it can sometimes
be seen and if it is a finite being.
Yeah, right, which we would say, um, except in the case of the Holy Spirit.
Um, if otherwise it is a finite being, then, uh, shouldn't it be made out of something?
Yeah, what's it's sort of matter?
Like a finite being, if it's not made out of something, then how would it be finite?
Right?
Yeah, it has to be circumscribed in some way.
And so you get these theories, right?
So you get...
like Aether, like is it a ethereal being, right?
Like so it's, it's made of Aether,
which is some kind of air, some kind of thick air.
You get Thomas Aquinas with the quintessence,
which is just sort of the fifth thing
that angels are made out of.
And you get not the sixth thing, it's the fifth thing.
The spiritist movement.
Okay.
with this idea of ectoplasm.
Yeah.
And thank goodness, you know, because now we get ghost busters.
Boop!
Yeah.
The apologies to Gwyneth Paltrow.
Why am I apologizing to her?
It's a racket.
Anyway, send the lawsuits to Father Andrew Damon.
See, that's one thing I won't take.
I'm not going to take any longer.
Yeah.
I'm insured.
Don't worry.
You will not be served.
We'll dance back as hard as you have to to make sure you are not served.
But yeah, so Ectoplasm, little, if you want to know more about Ectoplasm, in spiritism,
they, the various mediums, is the plural mediums still media if you're talking about people?
I don't, oh man, I don't know.
Anyway, various mediums.
You're sending me looking things up now.
with just mediums, larges and smalls.
So, right, if you don't have,
like if you're gonna say,
oh, I'm talking to your departed grandmother,
person whose name starts with Jay.
And, right, they're telling me XYZ, right?
People start to catch up and they're like,
Well, is there any actual evidence that you're talking?
to anything right or that anything's really happening other than the spooky lighting and the
you know whatever it is mean times by the way okay yeah is there any evidence and so
Echdoplasm is sort of concocted as a a a visual representation of the presence of a spirit
Ha!
Edd!
They would actually could cock some goop that they said was Ectoplasm.
Oh nice.
And it would be.
I mean, I'm having you can't do that on television flashbacks.
Yeah.
Did you ever watch the show?
Yeah, it was usually kind of clear and slimy.
Actually, not green.
Yeah.
And it means green and those slimers.
Slime actually canonically is clear, not green.
But anyway, that's true.
Yeah.
But so and then
It seems to have been first used by mediums who would sort of expel it from their mouth or other bodily orifices.
Nice.
To indicate that a spirit had come upon them.
But that was also used as things got sort of more advanced in theatrical.
They would sometimes have a person who they give sort of cakey makeup and have stand,
you know, kind of in the darkness who was supposed to be, you know, the...
the dead person, right? And they would have that person sort of expel goop
in various ways in order to identify this as a spirit. And people believe it. Yes.
That's just... But people believe all kinds of crazy stuff. It's hurt parts will now. I'm ready
to believe just about anything when someone says so-and-so did this. Like yeah, I'm sure they did.
Yeah, it's certain parts of Florida they still do
And yeah, Harry Houdini left a lot of good notes because he went around debunking a lot
of these people.
Huh.
I did not know that.
Yeah.
His mother had passed away and he had been in his grief sort of desperate to contact her.
But being Harry Houdini, he could identify Shaqainery pretty quickly.
and realize these were all
fakes and then decided and then got angry and decided to take them all down. But anyway, slight digression.
So scholarship named after him seems like a good way to memorialize that.
And no, and since it's at Northeast Pennsylvania, it should be at St. T. Conds. We need to get on that.
The Harry Houdini, yes, debunking spiritus nonsense scholarship. The Houdini museum is up there, man.
Wow, there is a Houdini-
fund the society of American magicians. So yeah, well, sometimes you want to disappear, you know.
But so this this points to a problem again, the reason we're bringing it all this up is not just
because it's kind of weird and cool, but it's October, but because it points to a flaw in our
thinking about spirits, right? Because again, we're trying to think of them as things. They've got to
to be made of.
something, right? We're thinking of them as things in a materialist sense, right? So they
must be some kind of object that's made of something, right? And that whether we can always
see it or not, they have to have a stable visual form.
Yeah. By the way, I have to say that we just got an um actually from YouTube. They said it's not
not very important in the long run, but Sebastian Shaw.
not David Prous appeared on Endorist Forest Moon.
Sorry for nerding out.
You don't have to be sorry for that.
Never, ever.
Not on this show.
We'll accept it.
Yeah, this is Sebastian Shaw, the actor.
Not the black king of the Hellfire Club in X-Men comics.
Correct.
Yes.
I caught that reference as well.
So.
Right.
So this is one sort of flotter.
thinking, right, is trying to think, trying to give them a body and think of what their body is made of,
and that points to the bigger problem, and the bigger problem is that we want to think of spirits as humans.
Right. We want to think of them as basically like us, right. And, you know, if we're talking about
the spirit of a departed human, then they are in some ways like us, right?
But in other ways not.
And if we're talking about a spirit that was never a human, right?
And then when you get to the Holy Spirit, especially, right?
Then they're definitely not like us, right?
So it's not just these are ethereal humans, right?
Or these are humans who have wings or these are humans who can turn invisible
or walk through walls or
whatever else, right? These are either not exactly a human now until the resurrection or not a human
at all. Yeah, and I mean you can tell that, I mean correct me if I'm getting this wrong, but you
can tell that this idea is really old because for instance when Christ appears after His resurrection
doesn't it say that the disciples suppose that they saw a spirit one of the time to encounter him.
Right, and he says handle B and C first.
spirit has not flesh and bones as you see that I have.
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So there's this idea where we want to treat them as other selves.
And this happens in other areas, right?
I mean, people do this with their pets, try to turn them into humans.
People do this with, right?
All kinds of non-human things.
But we also do this with...
with spirits, right? So spirit is not a subcategory of human, nor are human and
spirit subcategories of some third thing, right? Other than created being, but
then that includes everything except God. Right? So that's not helpful, right?
Right.
And so really instead of looking at a spirit as an other self,
someone...
else like us, we have to look at the spirit as another other. This is a different thing.
And so now that we've taken that negative approach, again, we're still not all that much
closer to what a spirit actually is. Right? Now that we've covered the reason to part.
We're trying to define it from 30,000 feet up like a sort of taxonomic.
Right. Yeah. Right. And when we've talked about...
Obviously, the show is called Lord of Spirits. We've talked about spirits a lot in different contexts.
And usually when we talk about them, we've talked about them from the top down.
Yeah. Right. We've talked about God creating them. We've talked about how like angelic beings and
then the saints are the means through which God administers His creation. We've talked about how
God has allowed the demonic spirits to rebel in order to use them for this greater
purpose.
us to bring about repentance in people.
Yeah, sort of big picture kind of cosmological stuff.
Right.
And we're not disavowing any of that, obviously.
But that entire approach doesn't help us with this question
of what spirits are, because we aren't up at the top
above them to look down on them.
Yeah.
Right.
We're not God.
So going from up...
top, right? And trying to understand what they are based on these, these things isn't going
to give us a definition. So as we move into our second half, teaser, we're going to be
going at this to answer this question, what is a spirit? We're going to be going in the
opposite direction. So going from the top down, we're going to go from the bottom up.
Okay, so we're going to start actually with things that are below humans and go to
and then work our way up to what a spirit is.
All righty, well, we're gonna go ahead
and take our first break
and we will be right back with more Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, I'm Alisa Biela Titch Davis. I love Sunday school and youth ministry, but I think
we all know that faith is formed in the home. Orthodoxy is not a collection of prefer. Check
out our ebook and audiobook. And if your family would love a weekly podcast where you
can learn about the faith together, join me and Christina Wenger on Tending the Garden of
of our hearts, a podcast for the whole family.
on Ancient Faith Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everyone.
It's the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
We just talked about...
about what spirits are not and gave some examples of what they are not.
As we mentioned at the end, we've been sort of taking a top down approach, looking at
spirits from kind of the grand cosmological story.
But now we're going to take it very much from the bottom up and begin with things lower
than ourselves.
So you're welcome to give us a ring at 855 AFRA DIO AF radio or 8552372346.
we would love to talk.
you during the second half of the show. Okay, so bottom up, right? Unless, unless you're
calling to defend that monster's movie because you're just being a contrarian. No, don't
even I hear you. Yeah, get away from it with that. Anyway, back to it. So opinionated father,
Steven. That calls him like I see them. Yeah.
All right. So where are we? We're going to talk about bats.
Yeah, we're going back to our friend Thomas Nagle.
Good old Thomas Nagle. Who?
And he doesn't know what it's like to be a bat.
No. And demonstrating to all of us that none of us do either.
Um, right. So, hey, there might be first time listeners.
Thomas Nagle, uh, rode a famous paper in philosophy called,
what does it like to be a bat?
Um.
Basically pointing out that we don't know and we can't know as humans.
We can imagine what it's like, what it would be like for our human consciousness and awareness to be in a bat body.
Because of like a witch or something.
Right.
For that horrible episode of TOS Katzpaw.
Yeah, I mean, I mean...
Believe it or not, there's actually a Wikipedia article about this called, what is it like to be a bat question mark?
So, um, right, but that's not what it's like to actually be a bat, right?
That's that humanizing again.
Yeah, right.
But what one of the things that paper presupposes is an idea regarding consciousness and awareness.
that is more recent than I think people realize.
Even in like the 19th century, somebody like Hagel, right?
Basically thought that animals were automotons.
They're like machines.
Yeah, that they just sort of pre-programmed and they do things based on
pre-programmed instinct.
Right.
But they don't have a constraint
a dog to do tricks, you were just reprogramming it essentially.
Yeah.
You dog doesn't love you.
He just...
Right.
You dog isn't aware that it exists.
Yeah.
There's no awareness.
Right.
And so consciousness was treated as sort of like, you know, binary, one or zero, right,
or like a light switch, right?
When you get to humans, the light's on.
Yeah.
Humans at the end of I mean we're talking about the 19th and early 20th century the end of evolution consciousness just appears
Right and it's accidental
In that in that kind of framework
But everything below humans on the scale
Was that a zero the lights are off right?
And that...
It's kind of counterintuitive to us even now.
Right.
Most people do believe that their dogs love them.
Yeah.
Well, but we got to be fair.
In the 19th century, people had pet dogs.
Right.
They were interacting with them.
It was just that there was not an acknowledgement of sort of consciousness, of reasoning, of, you
as we found out more and more of that animals have language.
right communicative abilities between them.
And so there was a revolution in philosophy of mind and in consciousness research to say,
hey, clearly a lot of these animals are conscious, right? They're able to actually make decisions
to choose to value one thing more than another thing.
They're not just purely driven by
impulse. And so, animals do have some kind of consciousness, some kind of awareness,
right? But it's at the same time as as a nega-less pointing out, that doesn't mean,
oh, what consciousness and awareness means for them is the same thing it means for a human.
But yeah, yeah, I mean, clearly your dog's consciousness is not as complex.
yours. Right. Sorry for people who, who, who started all those people out there
refer to their pets as their children. But I have one heathen dog who's pretty clever.
I believe in a devious way. And, and to be fair to the people talking about
dogs as their children, it is a scientific fact that when a dog owner looks
their dog in the eyes and pets them.
is secreted in their brain and the dog's brain as in a parent and a baby human.
How about that? So they're being chemically tricked into thinking that? No. To be fair to them.
That's that you've been in the South Long enough you're giving backhanded compliments. That's good.
Congratulations man. You've been inculturated.
but so Degels making the important point.
that what we say, okay, so these animals are conscious,
we're not just giving them a one instead of a zero.
Yeah.
Right.
But this is consciousness and awareness
is more of a continuum.
Right.
It's more that there are levels of consciousness
and levels of awareness.
And that the, and this is why,
so if we're trying to talk about like,
What is the consciousness or awareness of an
angel like, as we've said before the show, this is what we have no idea. Yeah. Right.
Any more than a dog understands what it's like to be a human. Right. We're a pig or a dolphin.
Knows what it's like to be a human. Whatever quote unquote smart animal you want to use.
A chimp. Right. Um, a bit no bow. And of course, then when you're talking about God,
is not even on this continual.
Right.
Look, this isn't even a rel-
category got this is a category of created beings right. So then the question becomes so if we
can all joke okay so there are these different levels of consciousness and there are levels of
consciousness above human consciousness and awareness and there are those below human consciousness
and awareness. Then the question is well where does that sort of end if we go below? Yeah do
Right. Do worms have conscious.
right. And so you know, does my oak tree have consciousness? Right. Is there a point where we get to a zero?
Right. Is there a point where we get to just the lights are out? Right. There's nothing. Right.
Zero Kelvin consciousness? Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. Yeah.
So one place we could suggest maybe drawing that line would be between animal
life and everything else.
So sure and earthworms consciousness would be super rudimentary.
Very low level, 0.001 if human consciousness is 1.
But then you could say, OK, well, that's the dividing line.
Is animal life versus everything else?
problem with that is that we're discovering more
and more that there is some kind of plant consciousness.
Yeah, like they are able to communicate,
some plants are able to kind of communicate with each other.
Like I've read about forests, for instance,
that pass information through their roots,
which is crazy to think about.
And not even just like aspens, right,
which is a single organism
with a whole bunch of things up top that look like trees,
They are trees I suppose.
But that separate organisms talk to each other.
You know, a very kind of,
if I may say so, fellowship of the ring
kind of moment with the old forrest, you know.
Just throwing that out there.
You're just sitting raw meat to be all one podcast people.
I know, I know.
But it's the concept is very relevant.
But yeah, and they've done studies recently where plants
where plants, they can't...
like on a tape play. Okay, kids a tape is a magnetic strip. They can take a
recording and you put a pencil in the one hole and you turn it. Yeah. So they
take a recording of the sound of water. So there is no actual water. It's just
the sound of running water like a stream. And they play it near a plant.
And the plants roots will start to move in that direction towards the sound,
that's crazy pants.
Right.
So yeah, so there, there, there, there are a lot of things like this that we're
discovering, right?
So okay, so instead of the earth, where it'd be zero point zero zero zero zero,
what we'll say.
A plant is zero point zero zero zero zero zero zero one right?
But basically we'll see.
we could say the dividing line is, well, something that's alive versus something that isn't.
Right? So like a rock. Right. But, but if we're understanding this kind of conscious awareness
as the ability to send receive process information, for example. Right? Then plate text.
would represent a type of consciousness.
Yeah.
Right.
That's kind of weird, you know, to imagine.
And a computer network.
Right.
Yeah. I mean, neural nets are completely inner, you know, in terms of biological life.
It's modeled after human brains, I guess, on some level.
although I don't really know anything about this stuff.
But that's what I've heard.
right? And so, right, we're not saying again, like the earth you could talk to it, right?
And it's like a woman. She would talk to you, right? Because that's humanizing, that's making
the humanizing mistake, right? Yes. But where we ultimately get to is that any ordered system
that transmits or processes information has some kind of at least tiny rudimentary level.
of consciousness. Yeah. Is somewhere toward the one end, toward the bottom end, but is on
sort of this spectrum of consciousness. Right. So that said, we're going to be hard on people's
heads, I think, with some of the second half. And by some. It's okay. We're ready to go there.
It's been a while since we did a...
of mind bending, but this time,
I talked about the mind in your stomach.
Yes.
Now, for the record, I don't want people to start calling me
Dr. Mindbender because I have a full head of hair,
and I lack his incredible mustache.
Yeah.
I have occasionally thought of buying a monocle,
but I don't think I could pull it off.
Someone's going to send you a monocle now, by the way.
I'll take a monical.
Yeah, they will watch it send me a monical like two times magnification. I will accept this as a gift.
Photos will be required of course. Yes. Well, that's fair enough. Right. That doesn't cost me anything.
So, um,
So one of the byproducts of what we just said, right, is going to be that any given organism.
and we're going to
use the human organism here as an example, because we can, as we were just saying, we
can best talk about human consciousness, right? That's the kind of consciousness and awareness
that we can know the most about and understand the best, because we're humans. Any dogs
listening, sorry, cats don't pay attention to anything, so we don't have to worry about
that. They're completely solopsistic. But so using a human as exhibit A, you contain
you
multiple systems that would have a level of consciousness.
Yeah. I mean, I heard people talk about like that your gut is kind of almost another
brain on some weird level. Yeah. Yeah. Your gut biome, the bacteria in your gut biome,
right? Who keep you alive, they communicate with the bacteria in other people's gut biomes
through the air.
Yeah, see that's creepy. I mean, I never watched Alien because as you know, I do not watch anything that even wreaks of being a horror film.
You know, on purpose.
The director is really good on Hulu.
Yeah, no, I'm not, no, not even a little bit. That's the one with the pins in the head, I think. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, no.
But yeah, the idea that there are gut bacteria.
that somehow are trading information inside me that are then speaking in some way to those.
And other people, I mean, that is kind of like alien level stuff right there.
They're having ongoing conversations with the rest of your media families gut biomes.
Ah, ha, ha.
House together.
This is scarier than last year's Halloween episode.
Right?
but that
They're bacteria, they're a separate organism.
Yeah, bacteria are not you,
but you certainly can't live without them.
And through that communication,
we were saying, see, there's a level,
there was a certain very low level
of consciousness going on there.
That is contained within you,
that is your gut bio, right?
This is true of some of the organs of our body.
So the human
heart regulates its own rhythm. And biological males and females of the human
species have slightly different heart rhythms. And if someone gets a heart
transplant from someone of the other biological sex, the their heart that
they receive will maintain its pre-
the previous rhythm in their body.
Right.
So it still beats like a girl or a boy.
And so other examples are the parts of your brain.
Right.
Yeah, there are parts that are kind of going off on their own and doing their own thing.
Your brainstem is not only like regulating your breathing and your heart rate and stuff.
Right.
Your brainstem is adjusting those things.
Right. It is receiving information from your body about the oxygen level of your body
and therefore causing you to breathe harder or to yawn.
I see we're all going to yawn now since you mentioned that.
Right. So and that's not the subject of your conscious thought.
No. Yeah. I'm not saying they're going, okay, time to yawn, go.
And your conscious awareness, right?
It's like a little separate stage manager in there.
Yeah, it's doing with the staging.
what to do. Your cerebellum is governing your balance, right? Emotion without you thinking about
it. Well, so you're saying that my brain has brains. Yes. Yes. Do they taste different parts,
taste different as zombies, or is that again last year's Halloween episode? The mind is a terrible
thing to taste. I feel like I ally upped that one for you there. Yes you did.
So that's a call back to a previous episode, right?
Couldn't remember that word.
Yes.
Thank you, everybody.
You wouldn't believe how many people wrote in to tell us that.
We must have gotten 10 Allie-Oop emails, at least.
Well, I'll generate some more emails.
All right.
Is calling that an Allie-Oop a reference to the old Allie-Oop 50s novelty song?
Oh, wow.
You know, I don't even know that one.
Or is it a reference to the comic strip Allie-Oop?
right in.
Let us know everybody.
Yes.
Right.
And then we could go to the, you know, different cells of the body
that are receiving information and regulating things
and processing, right?
So the human body then, right?
And so the human organism, you, the listener, right?
Are made up of a big pile of interconnected
Small consciousnesses that are all operating together to keep you alive and allow you to
function and do the things you do.
And then what we think of as our consciousness, as our awareness, our point of attention
our news, right, is something that comes in over the top of all of those sort of subsystems
that are all operating.
And so then what are we talking about then when we talk about that consciousness?
So this is what is called, right?
You see this in Aristotle, you see this in the church, fathers, you see this in St.
Maximus.
This is what we're talking about when we're talking about the natural will.
Yeah, right.
It's the natural will because it's related to our nature as a human.
this direct didness and propulsion that moves any given thing,
anything that has a nature, has a natural will,
that moves it toward its tell-os,
toward its perfection, toward its completion.
And so there are various elements of that,
for example, stay alive.
There's sort of these basic things.
Right.
And that natural
natural
will override or at least can override the individual sub-consciouses of the various elements.
So if you put your hand in a fire, you're not going to make a conscious decision to pull
it out.
Yeah, it's very much unconscious.
Right, the nerves.
Right, but that information goes...
somewhere and something pulls your hand out. Yeah. Right. But you're not making a conscious
decision to do it. But you can at least attempt to consciously keep your hand in the fire
despite the pain. Right. Right. Right. For some reason, for some larger reason. Right. Yeah.
An overriding thing. Right. Yeah. Like, like, if you, you know, if the if the gum jibar is being
being held to your throat for-
You might do right right here is the mind killer fear a little death leads to total obliteration anyway
So and then this natural will is where the human energy comes from our human activity
Right our human activity is the working out of
This natural will
Okay, yeah, which I mean
The theological technical term.
for this is energies, right?
Energy.
Yeah, working in the world.
Yeah.
Working, yeah.
Operation, if you need a Latinate word.
Right.
And so we're there.
A human spirit, what we're getting to here
is that a human spirit is this complex of faculties centered
around.
the natural will and energy.
Your will and your activity, that will and that activity
that comes over top, that comes over and above.
Sort of an organizing as an organizing principle, as a directing principle.
Yeah, but with the sense, with consciousness, you know, right exhibits consciousness. Yeah.
Right. Yeah.
Okay, so I mean if someone's trying to say well, what's my spirit? Could you say it's the me that I feel is me
right
That the well we're you're talking about the they're talking about the self. Yeah, okay. Yeah
Yeah, but I mean we all have we all have for instance this constant experience of being ourselves
right
Yeah, oh
Okay.
No, there's...
Yeah, I don't know what it's like to be anything else. Right, but there are also experiences
Right going back to our news episode
There are experiences of losing the concept of self
Okay, sure right right so yeah, so I don't want to hang a lot on itself
Right, okay, the idea of self, but this is something sort of adjacent
This is more again like when we talked about the news. We're talking about awareness
This is the lights being on.
We're not always aware of ourselves.
But we're always aware.
Awareness can be directed at other things other than ourselves.
Yes, please, everybody.
Even potentially to the point of self-forgetting.
We're talking about this overriding awareness.
We're talking about this natural will and activity of ourselves as a whole.
Okay. Right.
So that's a spirit right within a body, right?
And so what we're gonna say then about a spirit
not in a body is going to be parallel to that.
Hmm, right.
This is where it's gonna get harder people.
So, hey, spirit right of a disabody human
is that will and that activity, right?
That sort of complex
of faculties continues to exist but without the physical body, which it was animating,
which it was making alive.
That would be a disembodied spirit.
And it continues to exist in an unseen way.
So then this is what we're going to say about angelic beings.
Right.
This is what we're going to say about demonic beings.
That there is this will and this activity that exists without a material body,
a meat body that is animating and organizing in most cases.
Now there are cases like demonic possession.
but we'll get more to that kind of thing in a minute.
Yeah, yeah, okay, so just to kind of hit a couple of objections off of the past here.
You know, if you're talking about will and energy, will and activity that direct, you know,
even just a human person, human body, right?
But will activity direct groups of people, for instance, someone might say from a materialist
point of view like well, that's just your person.
perception, right, that it's just an observable sort of phenomenon.
It's not that there's some personal being actually doing that, you know, that like the
spirit of the age is just a metaphor, right?
But the reason why we would argue that that's not the case is that there is in fact will
into action. There's something more than just the collective set of...
whatever's right.
Will an action implies a subject?
Yeah, there's some one doing the willing and the acting.
Right.
And so this is actually how spirit is related to wind.
So here's a practical example from one of my heathen dogs.
Okay.
One of my dogs, Sasha.
She is goofy and adorable, not the sharpest tool in the shed.
Okay.
And she, if she is out in the backyard
and she's trying to do her business
or she's trying to figure out what a smell is
or whatever she's about in the backyard.
And the wind blows.
Right?
She doesn't understand what it is.
She thinks something is touching her.
or pushing on her, but then she turns towards it and she can't see anything. She does this all the time.
Yeah. Right. Like we can't take her outside to do her business when it's windy because of this.
She's just constantly distracted and freaking out about what's touching her. Yeah.
Right. There is this movement, there is this activity, there's something happening, but there's no visible
agent, right? No visible subject that's acting upon...
on her. This has become very poltergaced, you know. Right. And so she can't sort of,
sort of process that something's happening, there has to be something that's doing this.
Right. Even when we say the wind is blowing, right. Well, what's the wind if it's not the blowing?
Yeah, I mean it's not air.
Air might be being blown.
Right. So we even in speech have trouble with that. Right. We have to put an agent there
doing an activity. Right. Yeah. By the way, I just had to look this up.
Poultergeist literally means rumble ghost. Oh, there you go. Isn't that great?
rumble ghost.
There he is.
That's that's my band name.
So, um, is that a dead rumble fish?
Anyway, so this is why we get, you know, pricing the Holy Spirit blows where he will.
And no one knows where he comes, he's has come from or where he is going.
So this is sort of built into the concept in that way, right?
This is the connection to win is that wind is an analogy, right?
for something that is sort of an agency
with no immediately identifiable agent.
Right, and activity with no immediately identifiable actor.
Right, and so then who the particular spirit is
would be the actor or the agent or the one
right, doing the thing.
Right, but that's the idea connection there.
Okay.
And so...
When we talk about angelic beings now, angelic and demonic spirits, we're talking about
levels of consciousness as we said that are above the human that are sort of further
up that sliding scale.
Yeah, so they have a broader effect.
Right.
Well, they have another level of consciousness, right?
We can't describe it because we're not them, right?
We don't know exactly what that's like.
We don't know exactly...
exactly what that entails. But if consciousness is based on organization and transmission
of information, then the place to look for, right, these higher level of consciousness,
right, just as my human consciousness is of a higher level than the consciousness of
my organs or the bacteria in my gut or, uh, my cells, the place to look is then the next step
up in terms of organization.
Okay.
and computer communities.
So we're looking at a place, a community,
a clan, a tribe, a family, a people group.
Yeah.
And again, to kind of counter that,
to head another objection, a similar objection
off of the past, some might say,
well, families and communities are really just
a bunch of individuals who happen
to be doing things together, right?
They're like atoms.
What?
I mean, atoms, right?
Atoms do things together and they make molecules
and they make compounds and that's something more
and other than simply the collection of atoms.
Right, like, it's not just that it has.
Water has properties that hydrogen atoms
and oxygen atoms don't have.
Yeah, totally.
Yeah, right.
And so the hole is not just the some of its parts.
Right.
Yeah.
And this is obviously experientially true, too, right, that when one of these groups forms,
right, there is a level of consciousness above that of the individual human persons who
make it up, right, that has a kind of will and has a kind of activity.
Thanks a lot.
This from the bottom up is what ancient pagans,
ancient folks called the spirit of a place
or the spirit of a city or a people
or this clan or this family.
Yeah, and they didn't conceptualize it as a metaphor.
Right.
It is the identifier for that higher level of organization
and will.
And sometimes that will overrides
the will of individuals.
Yeah, that's where it gets.
weird and right and is willing to sacrifice certain of those individuals for the good of the whole organism right the way you might have granted the fire.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, and like an example that we know even from our own experience is that crowds of people tend to do things that individuals would not.
Right, you know, they have their own kind of mind. Right. Right.
that there's a spirit of a place in a time that people are caught up into. Right.
And so these collective units take on a will, right, of their own.
They have activities of their own, right, things that they work together, right, and do.
And so the spirit of that unit is the collection of the collective will and energy that has its
own overriding factor.
Right?
So then how does the person who is within one of these units, right?
Which we all are, right?
Modern culture has done its best, right, to atomize us and separate us from all of these.
And that's why we keep feeling like we're dying for the same reason that if I cut off my finger,
it wouldn't do well on its own, right?
Yeah.
Because...
Remember, the spirit is what animates the thing.
Right? It gives it life.
So the person who's in one of these,
right, there is this collective will and energy
of the whole, of the spirit of the whole.
And the person has to choose
whether to participate in, to take pardon,
to cooperate with, to synergize with, right?
Cinergaya, to take their will and their energy
and merge it, cooperate.
with that of the group order resist.
Yes, which, I mean, this is going to seem like a weird example,
but really it is the one that popped into my head,
which is why, you know, when I worked the 1997 Jimmy Buffett
concert at Hardy's walnut Creek in Royal and North Carolina,
concert goers could either choose to contribute
to the river of beer and vomit in the cable troughs,
or they could choose not to do that.
But you wouldn't think that contributing to that would be the kind of decision that someone individually would make.
But weirdly enough, a lot of people made that decision.
And then the poor stage hands had to pull those cables out of there.
So we were choosing actively obviously to resist it.
But yeah, I mean, there's, yeah, it's like that it would stock 99.
I avoided that quite on purpose.
Let that be listened to you all.
But yeah, there's, you know, when we've all had experiences like this where you're in a crowd of people, particularly, or even in just a small group of people and everything is kind of going one way or another.
Or just your family.
Yeah, yeah, just your own family.
Your family dynamic.
Okay.
Yes, right.
Family systems.
We talk about family systems.
Yeah.
And so,
This, this, what we're doing.
talking then about those systems, this gives us important language and understanding, right,
that we can only have from our Christian perspective, right? So, sometimes we're in a unit that the
spirit is like corrupt. Whether it's a family, whether it's right, just our culture, whether it's a
any other kind of group that we join and it's corrupt and it's evil and it's corrupting.
The language we need to understand the change is not just, hey, I need to go and convince all of
these folks, right, that what we're doing is a bad idea and hey, here's a good thing to do.
Yeah, it's not cognitive. It's not a collection of individuals.
Yeah, right? It has a life of its own.
the language we need to you
is the language of like exorcism. We need to remove the spirit that is there animating it now
and then understand how to invite a different one. Yeah. Right. Like getting rid of Aphrodite
and bringing in Saint Dmitrius if you're in Thessaloniki. Yeah. Yes. Right.
So yeah, this we have this idea.
Bread.
into us, regardless of what you think of it as a form of government of sort of democracy,
right? That all of these collectives are just individual,
bunch of individual people who all have their own thoughts and ideas, right? And any events that
happen, right, or any kind of larger movement of anything is just that there's a whole bunch of
of people who happen to have the same ideas.
Or who have bested each other.
Like vote.
Right.
It's all for like, yeah, yeah.
And if those people were all perfectly free to accept completely different ideas and if
they had, the things would have gone in the opposite direction.
Right.
Yeah.
And so we just need to go and reason with people and with individuals and convince enough of
them, right, to go this other way.
But again, that isn't how any of this works.
Right.
talked about recently on the show, these ideas come after.
the fact. These ideas come after the fact. In fact, we've talked about where thoughts
that ideas come from before. Yes, right. They come from outside. People are
from meable. They come from outside. Right. And so the ideas that are going to arise in
a community that's animated by a corrupt and evil spirit are going to be corrupt and evil
ideas. Right? 20th century history is full of this.
Yes, and it's not a question of irrationality, right?
Some of the people, you know, Maximilian Rovesphere was pretty sure he was the most rational
man on the planet.
Yeah.
Right.
Yeah, and I recall, I can't remember what I was reading this was from years ago, but I
I recall that a major turning point in terms of peoples.
awareness of this reality is in looking at the evil of the Holocaust because a lot of
what was going on in that was simply the sense of, well, so how do you kill millions
and millions of Jews? Well, it's basically a big engineering problem. They just sort of
solve that.
And the reason why I think that was in
some way the turning point and awareness of this was there was this idea that lots more
education equals a more moral world. But the level of education and sort of scientific
knowledge required to kill millions of Jews was very high, you know, as a big engineering
problem. And yet it did this deeply, deeply evil thing. But that's because there was a different
spirit animating that.
You know, right, right.
And, and I said I was gonna get in trouble later in the show, but what the heck.
So is this that moment?
Okay.
Everybody's maybe take out your pins on.
So right.
And people forget, right, that Hitler's original plan was to wipe out about 90% of the
slavs take their land
and enslave the rest.
To work for the glory of Germany.
Why was he going to do that?
Well, he looked at all the other nations in Europe, and this was built into European
culture and American culture, for that matter.
The way all of them became wealthy was through colonialism.
They went to other countries.
They killed, look at Belgium and the Congo, right?
killed most of the people and enslave the rest.
and therefore enriched their home country.
Yeah, I mean, this is what Empire does.
Right.
And Germany had no colonies.
So he decided to make some in Eastern Europe.
That's what the whole labor and the around plan was.
Right.
So this wasn't a thought that just Hitler had,
because he was a very naughty man.
Right, he was just an evil dude, born evil,
and so he came up with this horrible idea.
This idea was in the spirit of the age.
This is what everyone was doing.
Yeah.
This is what the-
The United States was doing it on its western frontier.
This is what all the nations of Europe were doing in their various colonies.
They were all doing this.
And so the idea came to them because it was in the air.
Right.
It was in the emigrated to that spirit of the age, the zeitgeist, in the spirit of the age,
right?
That's where it was.
So that is a sort of perfect example, right?
of these ideas.
emerging and then racial ideologies emerged out of that. These people weren't racist and so they
went and set up colonies. These people went and set up colonies and did this and then de-justify it.
They adopted racial ideology. Yeah, and you get, you know, eugenics and all those ideas again come
nasty stuff to justify what we're doing, right? Yeah, so yeah, these are these are
are perfect examples. This is where ideas come from. And so this is why what this is usually called
in the New Testament, the zeitgeist of the Spirit of the Age is the world. Yeah, to be distinguished
from the world as in the beginning God created the heavens and the earth. Right. Right.
The cosmos is in the creation, not the material creation. Yeah. The world is talking about the spirit
of the age. The powers and principles.
This is always demonic.
Yeah, and the Bible uses that word in both of those ways.
And it's important to distinguish.
Like when Christ said, he came to, you know,
not to condemn the world, but to save it.
He doesn't mean he did not come to condemn the spirit of the age,
but to save it, you know.
Right. Yeah.
Right.
St. Paul says that the deal is the God of this world.
Swalgy.
Right.
That's what he's talking about there.
And so Christianity has always been over against that and has always seen the thoughts and
ideas that come out of that as being what has to be fought and resisted in spiritual warfare
and in the Christian life.
So hopefully that gives a better idea, right, historically of what we're talking about.
And so what this means is that when the scriptures tell us to test the spirits, right, this
doesn't mean, hey, when a spirit appears to you.
Right? When the four-scope shows up, it says, I bring you a message, you give it some kind of quiz
to determine if it's an angel or a demon. Right? Yeah. Right? That's not what we're talking about.
Right? It's not a kind of taxonomic activity to determine what its species is.
You know, could you please provide a sample of your ectoplasm so I can take it back to the lab?
right. It's the spirits we encounter, the spirit we encounter.
in the woods, the spirit we encounter in our civic life, the spirit we encounter in our
parish community, the spirit we encounter in our family, the spirits we encounter,
right, determining whether this spirit is fallen or unfallen.
And this is the divide. Every spirit which is good, every spirit which is angelic is going to
the leaders to Christ.
Yeah.
What's every...
What direction is this...
taken what's the fruit? Every spirit which is fallen is going to lead us to destruction.
Yeah. And this is why, and this is why, you know, martyrs are essentially
dissidents against the spirit of the age. They will not comply with that.
you know, but we're not taught as Christians simply not to comply with any
any spirit that's not even a possibility, but rather to be conformed to the Holy Spirit,
right? But we're supposed to resist the spirit of the age. It's manifold, multi-ferious,
manifestations. And so Jupiter is not an idea somebody came up with someday.
Jupiter is the spirit that motivated Rome to go out and create a wasteland of the world and call it
piece. Yeah.
to quote Lively, or paraphrase Lively, right? And that's what the scriptures mean when they say all the gods of the nations are demons.
They are spirits which are leading you to destruction.
Yeah, yeah, it's funny because demons are these kind of lesser spirits and so
it's a sad commentary essentially like the nations are being led by these petty tyrants.
Yes, yeah, and that that's not just the hypothetical thing
where he's off somewhere, there's some demon who's like a black, dark, smoky, brimstoney
force ghost rubbing his hands together with horns of tail. Right? Like I'm going, you know,
here's what I'm going to get them to do, you know, and then he convinces people like to go along
with his plan by offering them things, right? Like that's not how it works, right? But that spirit
is at work. Right? And people...
experience it. They feel it when the Romans gathered together, when they held
one of their triumphs and paraded the slaves they'd taken, right, giving glory to
the general who won the victories, right? That spirit was there, right? Motivating it.
Everyone there encountered it and felt it there and chose to participate in it
and follow it and be transformed by it or to rebel against it and reject it. And
and there were consequences for the latter.
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, with that said, we're going to go ahead and take our second break and we will be right back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and with my co-host, Father Stephen DeYoung, I'm
one of the pod-fathers behind the ancient Faith Radio Live Callin' program, The Lord of
Spirits.
Father Stephen and I have been blown away by the overwhelming success and popularity
of our little show about angels, demons, saints, and yet giants too.
Apparently, there's a real hunger out there for content that addresses the spiritual reality
that permeates all of creation.
in spite of the rampant materialism of modern society.
But did you know that this programming on ancient faith radio is only made possible by its listeners?
Not only Lord of Spirits, but all of the live shows on AFR, Orthodoxy Live, Ancient Faith,
today, everyday Orthodox, search the scriptures, live at the lows and stewardship calling all of these
oh their existence to the generosity of people like you.
Without your monetary support, there wouldn't be marathon discussions of Zeus
or hate you.
or the Nephilim on Thursday nights. There wouldn't be an ancient faith radio at all.
Take the opportunity today to add your contribution to those of the other faithful AFR fans
who help keep shows like Lord of Spirits on the air. Participate in the Ministry of Ancient
Faith Radio, partner with us to bring the Orthodox Christian faith to the world. Become a donor
today by going to ancientfaith.com and clicking on Donate in the upper right hand corner.
Thanks, Lidman.
for your support.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You know, I almost completely forgot that I recorded that promo.
What?
So I hope people got the message, you know, of that important commercial, but I have to
say I was distracted by the best part of it, which was the public domain sports montage
music that was playing.
It's true.
We make use of royalty-free music on Ancient Fade.
And if people give to Ancient Faith maybe someday, I can just play clips of all these songs.
sub-reference. There you go. Well, that would be pretty expensive. Probably. Oh, come on. Yeah.
Rob, once in a while, once in a while though, we do actually purchase licenses for music.
So, you know, just putting that out there. But can I get William Shattner's version of Spirit in
the Sky? Oh, boy. You know, so we could, we could directly play a little clip of William Shattner's
spirit in the sky. If we were to
offer commentary about it. I can just gosh about it. Yeah right exactly so so that
would be then fallen to the fair use doctrine of copyright law but again it would
have to be clip and we would have to be through the purposes of commentary and review.
Especially when you get to the guitar solo in Frampton Peter Frampton just comes alive.
right right there's nothing better than a song written in performance
to buy a Jewish person about Christ.
Right. Yeah.
In the folk rock genre.
Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, I do have a soft spot in my heart
for the Norman Greenbound original.
Yes.
But it's Jewish also Jewish.
Right.
The Shadner version is pretty great.
Did I mention you by the way that Shadner is a Litvac?
He is of Lithuanian Jewish ancestry.
Yes, so just putting that out there.
Your N. Can you be in the list of pride is now?
It's not nationalistic pride, it's, I don't know what it is exactly, but yeah, they're Lithuania,
Uberalus, I know.
Wow, that's very dark considering where we just were in the...
Yeah, I know.
I know, no bounds.
Thank you for that, humility machine that is your dutchness.
All right, so it's the third half.
Feel free to give us a ring, 855 AF radio.
You'd love to talk to you about this.
spirits. But speaking of the spirit in the sky, that's what this third, third half of the
episode is about. So all right, where are we now? So now that we have some kind of at
least working if brain hurting, right, idea of what, what a spirit is here in our third
half, we're going to talk about how that applies to the Holy Spirit, right? Spirit capital
S. Spirit of God.
So spoilers where we're going to go with this, right, that the Holy Spirit is called the Holy
Spirit because he has an analogous function, right? He operates in a way that's analogous
to the things you're saying about spirit in a general sense.
Right. He is not a particular individual of a general category called spirits, right?
just like
God the Father is not a dad.
You know, your dad, he's not like your dad.
Right.
But there is an analogy of sorts.
And properly understood by the way, just to clarify.
In Orthodox understanding, the analogy go, this analogy goes top down.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Right.
So we're right.
We're the.
Heal more.
He said, the fatherhood of God is...
whence all other fatherhoods are named. Yeah. Yeah. Just like when St. Paul says that marriage
is like Christ in the church. Right. Not say Christ in the church is like marriage.
When the analogy is not that like the Holy Spirit is kind of like a created spirit,
it's the other way around. Yeah. Created spirits are. We refer to great spirits as spirits because
they are in some way analogous to the Holy Spirit. Yeah. As a turtle. Yeah. Yeah.
That important distinction.
All right, as you'd like to say, continuities and discontinuities.
So the Holy Spirit is called actually most commonly when he's directly referred to, other
than sort of the appearances we referred to in the first half.
He was referred to in the Old Testament as the Spirit of God, right?
And in the case of the Spirit of God, St. Paul, again, brings out sort of...
of the analogy, for example, in 1 Corinthians.
In chapter two, verse 11.
Yeah.
This is one of these verses that,
you don't hear a lot of sermons on.
Right.
I don't remember it yet.
I don't know, maybe you've preached a few.
Yes, so 1 Corinthians to 11,
For who knows a person's thoughts except the spirit of that person?
person, which is in him. So also no one comprehends the thoughts of God except the spirit of God.
Probably because it's just, it's not an easy verse to kind of suss out. It's not like,
okay, here's an inspirational verse, but I can really get, you know, that'll preach,
right? But there it is, 1 Corinthians 2 11.
Right, right. And as a side note, I'm going to be very contemporary in circles.
that you don't run in. But first Corinthians 2 verse 11 just on the face means that everything
that God the Father knows, the Spirit knows. Sorry, James White. Okay. I know who that is.
But you don't know what it's about. But anyway, it's true.
So in the New Testament, there are a lot of different ways the Holy Spirit is referred to.
the Holy Spirit being the most...
common one, but he is also referred to as the spirit of Christ. Right? And this plus what we've
said about spirits plus what we just saw, right? In 1 Corinthians 2 verse 11, connects it to the
idea of the mind of Christ. Right? Not that we're saying those are the same thing, right? But there's a
There's clearly kind of connection there, right?
And if spirit is referring to this consciousness and awareness and this complex, right, of faculties,
then that would make sense, right?
And so Saint Paul makes that analogy in Philippians.
Yeah.
Yeah, he says, you know, have this mind among yourselves which is yours in Christ Jesus,
which I like the fact that this transgress, this is the ESV, makes that very clearly plural.
There's some translations that have this...
mind in you, which, you know, in Greek it is plural, but in English of course it's ambiguous
because we've lost the vow, you know, the in this case, have this mind in yourself, among
yourselves, and I like also a monk. I mean this definitely has this kind of spirit.
Collective idea. Yeah. Yeah. Which is yours in Christ Jesus. If you're in Christ Jesus, then
And you have this mind among yourselves.
Right.
But.
But the place where Saint Paul gets most explicit and draws out and develops this the most,
right, is actually in another place in 1 Corinthians chapter 12.
And this is a famous, what's usually described as a famous analogy or a famous metaphor.
Right.
The body here to say, yeah, not a metaphor, not a metaphor, not an analogy.
Yeah, but
We need to read this in terms of what we were just saying in the second half about the way in which the spirit of a human person relates to their body.
Yeah, right.
And so, St. Paul is famously going to say that the church is the body of Christ.
Right.
And again, not a metaphor.
And he says, you are members of it.
And he's using members in the sense of bodily members.
Right?
Body parts.
He even gets one person's an eye and one person's a foot.
Right?
So he makes kind of explicit that that's
what he's talking about.
Yeah.
And so if we understand then a spirit
as this faculty that animates a body,
Right then what St. Paul is saying here is that is the Holy Spirit who shares the divine will and energy with the Father and the Son
Right the persons of the Trinity have one will and one energy right
That the Holy Spirit that is animating the
Church as a body
Making out of the diverse persons right a single organism
Yeah. And that human bodies are analogous to that. Just as, you know, the person that
is endrodemic actually consists of, as we mentioned, a bunch of self-regulating elements,
including organisms that are genetically other than I am, right, bacteria and such.
And yet they are...
necessarily part of who it is that I am. And that's a kind of lesser version of this,
right, of the body of Christ. Right. And for St. Paul, the way in which that animation of the
body works out is by the diversity of gifts, received from the Holy Spirit. That animation means
that each, each part, right?
each member, each organ within the organism, right?
Each cell within the organism is empowered by the Holy Spirit to perform its function,
is made alive in order to perform its function within the whole.
Right?
And then because a human person still has consciousness, right?
nature of human consciousness, you can choose
cooperate or to resist. Yeah, you could cooperate with the spirit with the Holy Spirit.
You can cooperate with God with the divine energy. You can resist. Right. Right. And I love
that word cooperate co operate. Right. You know, operation is together. Sinner. Yeah, if
you're going to need to use the Greek version, synergize. You know, but working together
to use good old fashioned plain English.
Right, and this is
Why from the very beginning, right, all the way back to the book of Exodus, right?
Why dissenters, right?
Why people who resist the resistor, the rebel, right, against the Holy Spirit, the one who
grieves the Holy Spirit, has to be removed from the body because they're like cells or organs
that have become cancerous.
Yeah, which are self, you know, they've gotten out of control and are only kind of serving them.
themselves, right? And our self-destructive, but if not removed, we'll destroy the body.
Yeah. Right. And this is why you always have, right? This means of removal. Right?
Right? If there is, but that's something they choose, right? Yeah. I mean, as difficult as it is
to, you know, countance that it's also just a reality. Unfortunately, right?
And so, this is what we mean.
Right? We say all the time, and we've said on this show,
that what we mean in the Orthodox Church by tradition
is not a bunch of secret stuff that we decided not to write down in the Bible,
that, you know, bishops find out about when they get consecrated.
Right? They tell them orally all the secret.
No one still writes it down.
But the other bishops come and whisper in their ear all the secret extra teachings.
Right? That's not how tradition works.
No, in fact they do-
You write it down.
Yes, everything is written down.
Yeah, when, like, at least in the Church of Antioch,
for instance, there is a tradition of a bishop
writing his profession of faith
in a big book that they have in the Patriarchate.
And he has to sit there and write it out by hand.
And the bishop who ordained me as a deacon,
Bishop Thomas, and didn't he make you a priest?
He did both for me.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
He's actually, as far as we know, he's the first bishop to write in that Antiochian patriarchal book, his confession of faith in English.
It's kind of cool.
But yeah, it has to be written out. It's not a secret whispery thing here.
So that's not what tradition is. It's not like the oral Torah in the Old Testament and that differentiates our view of tradition somewhat from the Roman Catholic view of tradition.
There's a separate source of authoritative teaching.
But we say that tradition is the life of the Holy Spirit in the church.
Well, that sounds nice.
It's also a little woo-woo if you don't understand what we're talking about.
Like, oh, okay.
You're just trying to take all the crazy stuff you do and say, God told you.
Right? Is that what you're doing?
That's not what we're doing.
But this is this understanding of the visible church as the material body.
Right, and the Holy Spirit is the
animating spirit of that body, right, is what we mean by that. Right. So the history of the church
is the history of this organism, body of Christ. It's ultimately the history of the life of Christ
in the world, right. But the Holy Spirit is the Spirit who's animating, right, that body.
Bye.
And so this is what we're talking about when we talk about tradition.
Right?
And so there are things that come into that life that are accepted, things that come into
that life that are rejected.
Right?
There are things which shift form, right?
There are things.
And that's all okay.
we have this right personal active understanding of the Holy Spirit.
and of tradition. And that allows us, as St. Paul is talking to the church in Corinth,
at the level of this individual Christian community in the city of Corinth about in the dead
center of the first century AD. And Corinth was about in the center of Greece at the
And so he's.
when he talks to them about the diversity of gifts and the diversity of the members,
he's talking about, you know, literally that what we would call a parish community.
And that there were different people there with different gifts, right?
They were who were part of the body in different ways.
But this is true on the macro scale too in both time and space, right?
This is why the Orthodox Church has always allowed for diversity in a whole lot of things
From length
to some of the details of liturgical ritual performance
to not just the language, but even the text
and what books are in the scriptures.
That all of these things are not only allowed for,
but they can be seen to be a good thing.
In that all of these are expressions of this life.
right and all of these different things
that are accepted and are part of the life and tradition of the church are all part of that diversity of organs within the organism that allow the whole organism to function and be what it is.
Hmm.
So, um, there's all kind of fits together in that way, right?
It's, it's, but it's kind of fractal.
It's at the level of the individual parish community, and then all the way up to the whole church, and then all the way up to the whole church.
throughout time. Right, which is why it's so hard to sort of pin down in a kind of objectifying way.
You know, this is the orthodox view of blank. Yeah, you know, it doesn't mean that there aren't
dogmas, right? It doesn't mean that. But if we try to use the kind of thinking that we use to
to create taxonomies of material.
stuff. And we try to turn that towards what the church is, then it's a total category
error, right? The animating will and energy of the church is the Holy Spirit. You can't
put the Spirit into a spreadsheet or a box. And by that, I don't mean that anything goes
right? Because there are different spirits that are trying to animate us. The question
to be in the Holy Spirit.
it to be in Christ. I think that's one of the problems is that there's this modernist assumption
that unless you're willing to put things in the boxes and you have to pick the right box,
that you're saying that anything goes. But that's simply not true. We see how the Holy Spirit is
consistent through the ages, for instance. There is a diversity, but it's a diversity within
and animated by the one Holy Spirit. Yeah, to do that kind of dissection and scientific kind of study,
The organism has to be dead.
And the church is an organism.
The body of Christ is unkillable.
So, out of luck on doing that.
So yeah, this also has the effect of meaning
that the visible church, the church
Right, the church has to be...
a visible thing made composed of actual human persons.
Yeah. It's not an abstraction.
And it's not just the list of all the people who believe in Jesus.
The Holy Spirit can't animate another spiritual entity.
Okay. So what do you mean by that?
Well the spirit animates a b-
body. Okay, right? Right. So if the your understanding of the church is as an abstraction
or as another spiritual entity itself is a spiritual entity. Yeah. Right. You don't have
a spirit animating another spirit. Right. Okay. All right. In that way, right? The wind
doesn't blow the wind. Right. That's get the
So that sort of completely fails to understand what St. Paul is saying, right?
Which again, it's not an analogy or metaphor, right? It's very real.
He's talking about, these are actual people, right, who make up the church.
So the way you get to the idea that the church is this invisible spiritual entity
will interview you in abstract categories.
something, you have to proceed from the basis of individualism again.
Right?
This is a collection of like-minded individuals.
Right.
Even if you just want to say, this is everybody who believes in Jesus.
Okay, this is everyone who has a certain idea.
Yeah.
That's right.
What what it is.
And that that would mean, right?
As we've been talking about all episode, that would mean that there is no spirit
Animating.
it. Right. That it's just a sum. Right. That would make the church the same as the Republican
party, the Democratic party, the Green Party. Which some people are treated that way. Right.
Right. Now, by the way, all those things I just named, I would hold there's a spirit animating
those two right yes right of course but right our person who wants to
see these things as collect all of these things as just collections of individuals who have the same ideas.
Right. That's the opposite of believing that there's a spirit and liveening and animating.
Yeah. Right. This entity. Right. And so this also means as we've talked about on the show before
several times in terms of what a body is. Right. That the church as the body of Christ is the embodiment
Okay.
Christ in the world. The Church is this nexus of powers and potentialities through which Christ acts in the world.
Yeah, I mean, isn't this what what St. Paul says in Ephesians? I can't remember the chapter where he says as
as he is so are we in the world. Right. You know that the church is Christ in the world. Truly. Right. You know and thus the beginning of the book of
right where St. Luke says, you know, in the previous
text, meaning the gospel of Luke, I wrote about all the things that Jesus began to do
and to teach, meaning that the Book of Acts is all the things that he continues to do
and to teach through the apostles.
Right.
And the church is to actualize the will and energy of Christ, the will and energy of the
the Triumphant God in the world.
And this is, directly, this is why.
I, like in the book of Revelation, when you see the beasts, right, who are the embodiment
of like world empire, starting with at St. John's time, the Roman Empire, right?
There are always this sort of flip side parody of the church.
Right?
So there's a mark of God that he puts on his people, so there's a mark of the beast.
Yeah.
A dark baptism, so to speak.
And the beast from the earth is sort of this.
evil looking sheep, right? This sort of fake lamb, right? Because
pressrooms portray this lamb because it's the flip side.
Because these empire, these pagan empires, these are
spirits, they're actualizing the powers of evil spirits, these
evil spirits in the world, right? The works of the evil one is,
as St. John says in first John. And you know, because people
get excited. This is what the giant clans are.
doing. Right? They're there. They're being the bodies of demons completely given over to this.
And of course, this is on a scale, but sort of the culmination of this is what's called
demonic possession. Right? In a negative sense in the New Testament, positive sense,
and some other things as we've talked about. Right? Where literally a person's body is just being
animated by an evil spirit.
Yeah, in the fullest...
your distrachiest sense. Yeah, and their human consciousness has just been sort of submerged
the way my gut biomes is by me. Yeah, that's, yeah, that's sort of the full,
sort of darkness of that. But this is also what when we talked way back at the beginning a little bit,
We broached some of the things for the 4th century that the the Holy Spirit
the church fathers in the four centuries said about the Holy Spirit. And this is what, for example,
St. Gregory the theologian sort of hammers on about the fact that in order to be able to
divinize or deify, right, in order for theosis to happen. So because that happens through the
Holy Spirit, the Holy Spirit must be God. So we say the Holy Spirit is divine, divine and deifying.
Yeah, this is who he is and what he's doing right and so
this happens again within the Church's organism. As we sort of conform our will and our activity
in the world to that of God through the Holy Spirit, who is animating and in liveening
the Church, following Christ. And so this is why the body of the Church is where salvation
happens.
Right, this is the the locus. Yeah. And this is why when the question comes up of salvation
outside the church, right, it's always a question of the Holy Spirit.
Hmm. Right. That's why St. Aaron Aesco straight to, we know where the Holy Spirit is.
He's animating the body of the church. We don't know where he isn't.
Right. Right.
There's spirits God.
No, no, no, no one will be drawn to Christ unless the spirit, you know, draws them.
Right.
So the spirit is at work.
The world are other places but like the wind, no one knows where he has come from or
where he is going, right?
But we know what he is doing in the church.
So this is why if someone comes to us, right, says what must I do to be saved?
We bring them into the church because that's the place where we know it's happening.
Right.
Yeah, and it's also why we know that when someone comes, the Holy Spirit has worked in them to do that.
Because that's what he, as the animating Spirit of the Church does,
is, you know, brings people in and conforms them to Christ.
Right. This is why he's identified over and over again as the giver of life.
Right, this is and live it.
right, making a live animating. Yeah, yeah. All right, well, some final closing
thoughts. You know, one of the things that happens a lot these days is people look
at evil happening in the world, especially when we look at it happening on
massive scale. But it doesn't just have to be in 2022, we mentioned...
some other evil happening earlier just in the 20th century. But I mean, this is human history.
But we know about the evil happening now. One of the things the questions people often ask is,
how could people do that? How could it come to this? I don't understand, right? And as modern
western people, I think most people listening to this probably that defines that describes them.
maybe not everybody, but modern Western people,
it's hard for us to understand this because we tend to be individualists.
And so when we ask, how could it come to this?
How could people do that?
How could this great evil have happened?
All we can conceive of is individual people making individual decisions.
And why would someone ever choose that?
We can't get inside their head why would they ever do that?
And why would all these people ever follow a person who leads them into evil, right?
But if we look with the eyes of the Christian tradition, the eyes of the scriptures, the
eyes of faithfulness, then we see that there are spirits animating.
people's individual people of course, that they do have a spirit about...
them. And when we recognize that, then it makes sense how you get these phenomena of
whole peoples doing evil things. But also how you can sometimes, thanks be to God, have whole
peoples who do good things. Right? Renewal does occur. The great renewal is still from our
point it.
you in the future with the resurrection and the end of the age, but there are lesser
renewals that can come.
And that is why as Christians, we always are people of hope.
And it's not because we think, well, enough people are going to get their minds changed.
And so eventually, we'll collectively have something better.
That's not what it's about.
Rather, it is that...
the spirit of God moves that the holy ones who are obedient to him move and there is a renewal
that occurs centered in the people of God. And that can benefit the whole world, right?
Even the people who are not part of the church as yet. And so we see renewals once in a while.
And we should be hopeful because we know that when
And we conform to that, then there is this animating character that we ourselves become
conformed to.
If we're individualists, we kind of don't like that idea, like don't make me do anything.
But the reality is that even if we try to be utter individualists and we try to resist
the Holy Spirit, then we are actually not being truly individualists.
are simply conforming to another spirit.
Or as we like to say on this podcast, sometimes there is no neutral ground.
You're either following the Spirit of God and being alive and by Him and being conformed
to His will and energy, or you're being conformed to the will and energy of a dark Spirit.
There's no middle ground.
It's just not a possibility.
And that's because as humans we are permeable, we are always being animated.
there's no way around it. So we have to choose, we have to choose to cooperate with the spirit of
God if we're going to become like him, if we're going to be like Christ, if we're going to receive
eternal salvation. The thing that's, well there's a lot of things that's profoundly hopeful about that,
but the one thing that I want to zero in on that's profoundly hopeful about that is that if we can
and lay aside our individualism.
Then we can choose to align our wills with God, but we also realize that the victory does not depend on any one of us, or even a collection of us.
We don't have to get enough votes in order for the world to be saved. That's not how this works.
It is an act truly of God.
And so then the question is, will I be on board with that or will I?
lie not. And to me, lifting that responsibility off of ourselves is is profoundly hopeful and freeing
because it means that there is a force, a good force, not the force, but there is a good spirit
at work in this world. There is a good spirit at work in this world, which is above and beyond all
are those spirits, he is the Lord of spirits. Right? So...
Yeah, this is kind of a tough episode in some ways to really, you know, a little bit of
mind bending.
It's been a while since we did one of those, but I think it's good for us.
And I believe also that we, having learned some of this, then our ability to read the
scriptures is enriched and deepened.
Like, especially take a look at 1 Corinthians chapter 12, you know, where St. Paul talks about
the body of Christ.
But at the beginning of the chapter, he's talking about the spirit.
fancy that, right? He begins talking about the spirit and he talks about how
there been led away from idolatry and they now are in the spirit of God and
the spirit of God gives gifts and the spirit of God makes us the body of Christ.
So yeah, check out 1 Corinthians 12, having listened to everything that we just said
and I think you're gonna read read it in a very different way and I hope a very
beautiful and hopeful and frankly encouraging.
kind of way. So father. So a great man once said, I'm not here to take the
temperature. I'm here to change the thermostat. And I've been honest about the
fact that I don't read all the emails. If you want me to read your email, the
best thing to do is just be hyperbolicly and insanely critical of me.
you
It's true. So if you, for example, go on Goodreads and write a 2,000 word
grade about one of my books about how the evilest man who has ever lived,
rest assured, I will read it and enjoy it thoroughly. But one, one thing I notice
is I go out trying to find criticism of myself. One thing I've seen, sometimes,
about Lord of Sp-
is that we have some folks who will say, you know, they like the show, but that essentially
Father Andrew and I are too sectarian. That we, you know, we present information, we present
things that they want to hear and are eager to hear and they're helpful to them.
But...
that we place that within this grid of orthodoxy,
they don't accept or don't want to accept or aren't interested in.
So they wish that we would just sort of give them the information in a way
that they could fit it into their current grid,
their current paradigm, their current understanding from some other Christian group
or some other group in general, or just their own personal views.
Um, and...
We're not going to do that, but the reason for that is that quote I started out with.
We're not here to take the temperature.
We're here to change the thermostat because one of the things that has most greatly hindered
our church life and our lives and influences Christians in the modern
world. And this isn't it's in it hasn't hindered God, right? But it's hindered us, right?
Is we have a set of self-imposed limits that we don't even realize our self-imposed limits
because we've inherited this whole framework for understanding the world and understanding
human activity and understanding the way the world works and politics works and religion
works and history works, that's all based around principles that are fundamentally not Christian,
that are based in sort of hyper individualism, that are based in materialism, that are based
in a secularism that concretely means that religion is purely a set of ideas, or disassociate
embole at least from everything else.
We've inherited it all.
this. And by holding to this, we sort of limit our own horizon and limit our own possibilities.
We limit what can happen in our parishes, in our families, in our own lives, in our
communities, our civic life, in the life of the countries we live in, in the life of
the world, we put these limits. This is what we can do. Again, God isn't limited by
them.
Right.
And so what I at least hope to do with this show, and I've always hoped to do with this
show, is not just feed a little more information into that hopper.
Not just sort of expand the paradigm a little with some new thoughts, right?
Not just sort of adjust the thermostat that's already there.
to try to bring a complete...
New way that isn't really new. It's new to us, right? But not new. Like paraphrase St. John
and in first John, new and not new at the same time. And new to us, whole paradigm for
understanding who we are, what the world is, how it works, what's in it, how it relates
to each other. And then based on that, a new understanding of ethics and new understanding
of
politics, a new understanding of history, a new understanding of all of that.
Which again, isn't really new.
It's always been there, but maybe now new to us.
And so that means we can't just tinker with the dials.
We can't just rearrange the furniture a little bit.
We can't just slap a new coat of paint, right?
We have to overturn everything and start over again.
Right.
paraphrase Nietzsche, we have to re-value.
all our values. We have to look at all the things we've thought were most
precious and most important and say how important are they real it really? And what
is really important? Right? How are we to live? What does it mean to be a
Christian? What are we to be doing in the world? And when we're willing to do that,
right, when we're willing to do that, it's not easy, right? I'm still doing it.
Everybody's still doing it. Who's even trying to do it is still in progress.
But what?
When we do that, the first effect it has is that those limitations disappear.
The limitations we put on ourselves disappear.
The things we think in a wild dream and then say, come on, right?
Those things all of a sudden become thinkable and possible and even doable, right?
Because we are no longer limiting ourselves to, well, I'm never going to be able to convince
enough people to go along with it.
right or you know there's just not enough money for this or that kind of thing
doesn't happen anymore. I believe it used to happen back in the church. You know I'm
not denying that the saints did this or that or that this or that happened but it
doesn't happen anymore. It doesn't happen to me for sure. It doesn't happen in our
parish. It doesn't happen in our city. Right. All of those limitations sort of
disappear. Right? Because the Holy
spirit is God, meaning he can do anything. He can do anything he wills. And that means
that we can do anything, as St. Paul tells us, when what we're doing is cooperating with
that will. Your parish can be transformed, your family can be transformed, your city
can be transformed. Any country on this
planet can be transformed. This whole planet can be transformed.
And it doesn't require you winning an argument coming up with a brilliant idea.
Doesn't require any of that. It just requires each of us for ourselves to cooperate with God
and with what he is doing in the world. And then things start to transform and they start
to happen for us, right, for us. And great and one.
wonderful and amazing things can happen.
So, I, when, even in this episode, and I know I do this a lot, when I say sorry, Calvinist, or I say sorry, somebody else took a shot at James White earlier this episode,
what I do that, I'm really not doing that out of a kind of chauvinism or out of a team spirit for the internet of church, you know, my dad can beat up your dad, right?
I'm doing that.
because the kind of transformation that needs to happen isn't going to be
possible for me. I'll speak for myself under those other paradigms and ways of
thinking. And we're saying that here's how you should understand spirits, not as
as just this exotic and interesting thing, ooh, I'm into this weird stuff, right?
But because this understanding is going to open things up for people, we hope.
I may be wrong about some of it, but we hope it's going to open things up for people.
It's going to make things possible for people that they didn't see as possible before,
because they didn't see them as possible before for them they weren't.
That's always the goal.
The goal is to try to set you free from some of the shackles.
that the spirit of the age has put on all of us.
And so hopefully that's what we're doing.
And so yes, I will be kind of a radical sometimes,
right, in calling for these things.
And if you're able to listen to the show
as someone who's not orthodox
and who disagrees with, say half of what I say,
and you're able to find things that are,
individual things are helpful for you,
God bless you, right, you do you, okay.
But that's never going to be like our goal.
That's never going to be what we set out to do.
What we're going to set out to do is to try to change everything and liberate everyone.
Which sounds crazy, except for the fact that we're hoping that we're doing this in tandem with the Holy Spirit who's got himself.
Amen.
Well, that is a
our show for tonight. Thank you everyone for listening. If you didn't get
through to us live, we'd still love to hear from you. You can email us at Lord
of Spirit, St. Anciente Faith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page or you
can leave us a voicemail at SpeakBife.com slash Lord of Spirit. And join us for
our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7
PM Eastern 4% including next time our annual Halloween. That's right. Halloween
episode next time everybody and if you are on Facebook
you can like our page and join our discussion group,
you can leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share the show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it and benefit from it.
And finally, obey the public domain sports montage music
and go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support.
We help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
And hey, everybody, tomorrow, Friday,
the 14th of October, there should be a new Ancient Faith
Radio app in your app store on your phone.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders
And the number of them was 10,000 times
ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor
and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.